So, just based on this, for those who have been working with web apps for a while, you
might already start to realize there's a lot of flexibility with this, because now all
of a sudden, if you have a back end that's not quite ready to integrate all the build
tools and everything you need to get it up and running, you can just on a specific page
when you're proposing to start progressively migrating your apps, you can say on this
page we're going to drop the CDN and we're going to add the basically interactivity
to this page and over time will migrate away and then once we have enough pages that consolidate
that view, then we can actually invest the time to do the build tools.
Because I think a lot of times when we think about migration, a lot of times developers
are thinking like code freeze everything, no new features, and we just stop development.
And we know that practically speaking, that just rarely works for business.
And so this is a really great way for us to basically go ahead and migrate an enterprise
app over to something that might use more modern framework technologies.
Now that said, we have a message here.
Now what if we wanted to, let's say, show or hide it based on whether or not the message
is even or not?
Well, something that View is also known for are their directives.
And so for those who have come from Angular, this might look a little bit familiar.
So the way that it works is that we basically would have a normal HTML element.
So let's say let's wrap this in a P element.
And then this one we're going to say even.
And this one we're going to say odd.
And so the idea here being that what we'd like to do is if the message.length is even,
show the even keyword, otherwise show the odd keyword.
And so one way we can do this is we can use something called view directives.
And the way it works is it's basically an attribute you add on an HTML element, and
it's prefixed with v dash.
So in this case, if I go v dash if equals message.length, and I'll use the modular 2
equals 0 to determine that it's even.
And then otherwise, v else, it'll display the other thing.
So if we refresh this, we'll see, ah, OK, there we go.
We'll notice that it is currently odd.
And so now if I delete the exclamation mark, that should bring us over to even.
And so what we see here is, again, one of the things I talked about when it came to
view is that it builds on top of what you already know.
And so when most people are working with HTML and CSS,
there's a lot of value in extending upon people's existing knowledge when it comes
to extending APIs.
And so in this regard, by basically having the convention of the v dash and
then using the if-else statements.
Again, if you know JavaScript, in fact, you don't even need to know JavaScript.
People would actually understand this property, granted, maybe not this part.
But when people are navigating the HTML,
they would actually understand what's going on here.
Rather than if you had kind of big if-else blogs that have a bunch of functions in it,
which again, I think sometimes we find is a little bit tricky with,
I think, sort of React components, those can be harder to follow.
Especially if you don't have as much experience with JavaScript.
But this here keeps a visually a semantic concise way of telling people what's going on.
Now, the other directive that I want to talk about is this one.
But before we do that, here's a slide to talk about this.
And this is from a while ago from Sansa Cone.
And what it says here is that 99.7% of software development in one requirement.
A user should be able to view a list of items.
And I still think that's incredibly relevant today, right?
That's what we're doing half the time.
We're taking a bunch of data, rendering out a list.
And I don't know about you all, but when I was doing this in React originally,
I realized there's a lot of different ways to do it.
And I know that there's more of a best practice now.
But that can be confusing for users, especially if they have a function that
runs the map or maybe in this case, use the for loop.
There's a lot of kind of deciding what to do.
And so let's go ahead and show how rendering a list works in view.
So in this case, I'm just going to do a list of numbers here, just to keep it easy.
And so one, two, three, four, five, and we have an array here.
And then what we're going to do here is we're just going to do an unordered list.
And then what are we trying to repeat, right?
We're trying to repeat the list item.
So what we're going to have is, if you might want to guess,
is that we have the v4 directive, right?
Using the for loop concept from JavaScript.
And what are we looping for?
For every number in list of numbers, we're going to go ahead and
just put the number.
That's it.
And if you refresh, there you go, done.
Your list is rendered, it's fantastic.
And so what's really nice about this, once again, is that we are trying to extend
upon people's base knowledge of JavaScript without getting too much in the weeds.
Again, the syntax is written in a way that's approachable for
people to sort of like in plain English, really.
For number in list of numbers, print number.
Great, I understand what that means, even if I don't know JavaScript.
The other fun fact about the declarative rendering of the curly braces here is
that it's not meant to just print out variables.
It actually does evaluate JavaScript statements in there.
So if in the case of, let's say we wanted to be really excited about the fact that
it's even, we can actually do two uppercase in here and run it.
And then you'll see that it'll actually transform the text,
basically run the JavaScript inside of it immediately.
So theoretically, you could also do things like, well,
let's just multiply like math.random in here and we refresh this, boom.
I mean, please, we have some interesting numbers up here.
But that's something to consider.
Now, the thing about this is when people discover this,
sometimes they get really carried away.
And we're talking like ternary statements and ternary statements.
And that to me is very, I would say, anti-view ethos in that we're trying to
make it easy for people to understand the code base, right?
So I would say when it comes to basically inlining your JavaScript
inside of these double curly braces, I would say keep it to a minimum and
try to abstract that logic as much as humanly possible.
So the question we have here is in regard to the differences between the View2Way
and the View3Way.
So the View3Way, as we see here, is that you can abstract a helper function from
View or if for those familiar with the View2Way, we had View, it was NewView.
You would instantiate a NewView app this way.
And so part of the reason this approach has changed is because View3 has
become a lot about becoming modular and performant.
In other words, being able to split apart things that you don't need.
With this sort of NewView approach, basically you have everything instantiated
with it and it was a lot harder from a bundling perspective,
like thinking of it from a library maintenance perspective.
That was a lot of the motivation behind this new approach,
which you'll see a lot more in View3CodeBases is that there's a lot of helper
functions which we'll actually see in this workshop that allow you to basically
break apart pieces of View that are helpful in certain instances.
And otherwise, it'll know to either drop certain things and optimize itself away.
I expected that V4 inside the UL instead of in LI.
So the question here is around the idea of the V4 element being like basically
someone having the impression that they thought that they would put it on the UL
element.
But the reason why this is not the case is because we have to think through what
exactly we want the renderer to be looping through, right?
What is the element we're repeating?
And in this case, we're repeating the list in this regard and not say like,
we don't want the entire unordered list.
So for example, if we did this, you'll see, we'll just show the difference.
So we can do it like this.
And if we refresh it, you'll notice that at first glance it kind of looks the same.
But when we take a look underneath,
you'll see that there are individual unordered lists happening in this case.
So don't get me wrong.
If in the case, you have a bunch of like, okay, let's just actually give that example.
If in the case, we have different things that we're going on in each element.
So let's say that, okay, so one, two, three, four, five.
So we have like an object here.
And let's say like name, let me do text pastry one to three.
And then ID, let's just do text pastry UUID.
Whoop, I need that first text pastry UUID, boom.
Okay, save.
Okay, so here we have a more complex data set, right?
We have a bunch of objects in each.
So if I refresh this now, you might notice that, well, nothing to do.
Did I mess something up syntax wise?
Do you have some math on that?
Oh, I am doing math, okay, that totally makes sense.
All right, okay, here we go.
Now if I save this, so in this particular case, maybe then inside of here,
we then have a like a sub list.
So I realize I actually didn't even add the other thing I needed.
So we could even say inside of here, we had another list inside of here.
That was then one, two, three, for example.
Then we might say, for example, in this particular list,
we want the first item to show the ID.
So we say number.ID.
And then we could then embed a second list and
that's where we would loop through number.list like this.
So instead of number, I'm going to say, switch this to item,
because now this is more accurate.
And then number in number list and then number like this.
So then we refresh this.
I broke something.
Item list.
Number and number list should be number and item list.
Number, yes, good catch.
Okay, there we go.
And so that's an example where you might want to loop possibly.
Although at that point, it might even be a div.
It's kind of you wondering why you'd want just the one.
But basically, consider basically how you want the semantic HTML to be
rendered out at the end of the day.
And that's the key thing.
A quick note before the next question.
In case anyone was wondering how I sort of did the data population,
that is the text pastry VS code extension that's highly underutilized.
But it's really great at generating things on the fly as far as ranges and
also custom UUIDs, which is great for random data when you're doing
some sandbox coding like I did.
Next question.
Is that data attribute and the create app?
Is that required or can we rename it to something like state?
So the question here is around this particular keyword data here.
In this particular context, when you're passing a configuration object to
create app, this is basically a reserved keyword in that it is called data and
that's what it has to be.
However, I will tell you right now that if you're more of a fan of calling it state,
there is going to be another style of components that we'll be covering that
will allow you to basically name things as you see fit.
But basically what you're seeing here is basically a preview of what is known in
view two or will view two and view three as the options API in that view will
provide you a set of options to do what you need to do inside of your app.
And those configuration and rail guards are actually, in my opinion,
very powerful when it comes to people either onboarding to view for
the first time or when they're looking to set like a standard and
consistency across their team, options API can be incredibly powerful.
But we'll show a little bit more about how that works before we get into the other
one, which is composition API, which for the person who asked that question,
you might be more interested in when we get to that one.